Guide to the American Irish Citizens Committee for the Re-Election of Mayor William O'Dwyer Records AIA.002
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
American Irish Citizens Committee for the Re-Election of Mayor William O'Dwyer Records
1949-1950
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Cudahy, Dorothy Hayden, 1922-2010
AIA.002
1.25 Linear Feet in 1 manuscript box and 1 oversize folder
The American Irish Citizens Committee for the Re-Election of Mayor William O'Dwyer was formed in 1949 and grew out of a previous entity, the Mayo Men's Committee for the Election of O'Dwyer, Joseph, and Impelletteri. O'Dwyer (1890-1964), a native of Bohola, County Mayo, Ireland, had been elected Mayor of New York in 1945. His 1949 re-election ticket included City Council President Vincent R. Impellitteri and Comptroller Lazarus Joseph. This collection includes reports, minutes, correspondence, financial records, press releases, advertisements, and other printed material generated by the Committee during the 1949 campaign.
Custodial History Note
Gift of Dorothy Hayden Cudahy in 1996. This collection was part of an accession of materials from Dorothy Hayden Cudahy, who was secretary of the committee and therefore kept the most complete records of its activities. The accession number associated with this collection is 1996.003.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
The American Irish Citizens Committee for the Re-Election of Mayor William O'Dwyer was formed in 1949 to help re-elect O'Dwyer to a second term as Mayor of New York City. It grew out of a previous entity, the Mayo Men's Committee for the Election of O'Dwyer, Joseph, and Impelletteri. Included on O'Dwyer's re-election ticket were City Council President Vincent R. Impellitteri and Comptroller Lazarus Joseph. With their headquarters based in the Hotel Commodore on 42nd Street and Lexington Avenue, the committee worked to raise funds, generate publicity, and successfully turn out the Irish vote for the three candidates. Officers of the Committee included: Martin Killeen, Chairman; John Kerry O'Donnell, Treasurer; James FitzPatrick, Financial Secretary; and Hon. Francis T. Murphy, Chairman, Executive Board.
William O'Dwyer (1890-1964), a native of Bohola, County Mayo in Ireland, emigrated to New York City in 1910. Prior to becoming Mayor in 1946, he served in the United States Army and later worked as a policeman, lawyer, district attorney. He was re-elected in November 1949 and served until August 1950, when he accepted the position of U.S. Ambassador to Mexico.
Sources:
McNickle, Chris. To Be Mayor of New York. NY: Columbia University Press, 1993.
O'Dwyer, William (with Paul O'Dwyer). Beyond the Golden Door. Jamaica, NY: St. Johns University Press, 1987.
Related Archival Materials
Mayor William O'Dwyer's papers are at the New York City Department of Records and Information Services, Municipal Archives.
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of reports and minutes, correspondence, financial records, press releases, newspaper ads, radio scripts and printed material generated by the committee from registration week to Election Day, 1949. Of particular interest is the pamphlet This Is O'Dwyer, produced by the committee. Also included in this collection is a newspaper advertisement for the election of William O'Dwyer from his first mayoral campaign in 1945.
Arrangement
The material is arranged alphabetically. An oversize box of advertisements follows the subject files.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Dorothy Hayden Cudahy in 1996. This collection was part of an accession of materials from Dorothy Hayden Cudahy, who was secretary of the committee and therefore kept the most complete records of its activities. The accession number associated with this gift is 1996.003
Minutes (administrative records); Irish Americans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Politics and government.; Irish Americans -- New York (State) -- New York -- Political activity.; New York (N.Y.).; Printed material.; Advertisements.; Press releases.; Irish Americans -- New York (N.Y.); Financial records; Impellitteri, Vincent R. (Vincent Richard), 1900-1987; FitzPatrick, James; American Irish Labor Leaders for O'Dwyer; O'Dwyer, William, 1890-1964; American Irish Citizens Committee for the Re-Election of Mayor William O'Dwyer; Murphy, Francis T.; O'Donnell, John Kerry; Joseph, Lazarus, 1891-1966; Killeen, Martin
- American Irish Labor Leaders for O'Dwyer, 1949; cuid14921 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Committee Members, 1949; cuid14922 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1949; cuid14923 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Financial records: Account Book, 1949; cuid14924 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Financial records: Bills Paid, 1949; cuid14925 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Financial records: Chase Manhattan Bank, 1949; cuid14926 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Financial records: Contributions and Expenses, 1949; cuid14927 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Newspaper Advertisements, 1949; cuid14928 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Photographs, 1949; cuid14929 (Box 1, Folder 8A)
- Press Releases, 1949; cuid14930 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Printed material, 1949; cuid14931 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Radio Publicity, 1949; cuid14932 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Reports and Minutes, 1949; cuid14933 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Speakers Committee, 1949; cuid14934 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Testimonial Luncheon in Honor of Mayor William O'Dwyer, Mar 1949; cuid14935 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- This is O'Dwyer pamphlet, 1949; cuid14936 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Volunteers (names on cards), 1949; cuid14937 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Newspaper Advertisements: "American Irish Brooklyn Committee for the Election of William O'Dwyer," The Irish Echo, The Irish World and American Industrial Liberator, Oct 6, 1945-Nov 5, 1949; cuid14938 (Box Shared Tamiment AIAOS001)